Guide to the Leonid Tsypkin Papers M2209
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Leonid Tsypkin papers
1947-2013
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
T︠S︡ypkin, Leonid, 1926-1982
Tsypkin, Mikhail
M2209
5 Linear Feet (11 boxes)
Typescripts, manuscripts, correspondence, and documents relating to the literary output and the private life of Russian author Leonid Tsypkin (1926-1982).
Content Description
This archive was collected by Leonid Tsypkin’s son, Mikhail Tsypkin, and consists of manuscripts and typescripts; correspondence both from and regarding his father; several of his parents’ personal documents; his father’s published works and reviews of them collected by Mikhail; some of Tsypkin’s books taken from his personal library; a large amount of his photographs; and the only known recording of Leonid Tsypkin’s voice.
The series of manuscripts and typescripts includes the original copy of Leto v Badene (Summer in Baden-Baden) – typed double-sided on a thick paper for smuggling out of the USSR; the original handwritten manuscript of N orartakir; carbon copies of both, as well as carbon copies of the typescript of his other novella, Most cherez Neroch’ (The Bridge Over the Neroch); original manuscripts and typescripts complete with Tsypkin’s own notes of his unpublished poetry, an unpublished essay, as well as all his short stories: both those still unpublished and those which have been subsequently published.
The personal documents here provide some insight into Tsypkin’s life with his wife, Natalia Iosifovna Michnikova through their diplomas, proof of employment, and Tsypkin’s resume among other documents.
The correspondence includes seven letters from the pianist Maria Iudina, who was the inspiration behind Tsypkin’s story Ave Maria! The largest section is the correspondence from Leonid Tsypkin and Natalia Michnikova to their son after he had left for the United States (dated July 21, 1977 to July 8, 1982) in which they discuss their lives. The series also contains letters to Mikhail Tsypkin from the same period from Klara Rozental’, the inspiration behind Galya in Leto v Badene), and to whom the novel is dedicated. The series also includes all of Mikhail Tsypkin’s correspondence connected with his effort to help his parents emigrate, including letters from the desks of Senators Edward Kennedy, Paul Tsongas, and Daniel Moynihan, the American Jewish Committee, Action for Soviet Jewry, and the letters of support written on behalf of the Tsypkins and sent directly to Leonid Brezhnev. Also included are both Natalia Michnikova’s and Mikhail Tsypkin’s correspondence with various literary journals and publishing houses, as well as Mikhail’s correspondence from 2001 to 2008 with Lucy Ravkina, a former colleague and friend of his father, who has included her memories of their friendship in his final years.
The archive contains whatever original publications of Tsypkin’s works that his son could acquire, as well as reviews and articles from the international press, collected by Mikhail. The ‘Library’ series contains books from Tsypkin’s own personal library. Chosen by Mikhail for inclusion here, they are primarily books connected with Dostoevsky, who was the subject of Leto v Badene and indeed the primary subject of Tsypkin’s interest for most of his life. Of particular note is Tsypkin’s own personal copy of Anna Dostoevskaia’s Dnevnik 1867 goda (Diary of 1867), which he had trimmed and rebound and which is described in and serves as a focal point of Leto v Badene.
There are also a large number of photographs included in the collection, reflecting how seriously Tsypkin took his hobby. The majority of the photographs are also connected with Dostoevsky and come from three cities associated with him: St. Petersburg/Leningrad, Moscow, and Staraia Russa. Many of them include Tsypkin’s meticulously researched notes and references. The photographs of Leningrad were presented by Tsypkin at the Dostoevsky Museum and this series also contains the text of the presentation he gave there.
Finally, this archive contains one audio tape, and is the only known recording of the author’s voice, saying a few personal words to his son.
Mikhail Tsypkin ordered and arranged his father’s papers and the general categories encountered there have been retained. Name and titles have been transliterated according to the simplified American Library of Congress of Standards, and an English translation provided where appropriate.
Biographical / Historical
Leonid Borisovich Tsypkin was born in Minsk, USSR on March 20, 1926 to Russian-Jewish parents. His father was a successful doctor in Minsk and was able to arrange for the family to be evacuated during the War. He returned to Minsk after the War and graduated from medical school in 1947. Tsypkin moved to the Moscow Region, and then to Moscow, where he advanced his medical career (authoring or co-authoring over 100 academic articles) and continued his education, receiving his Doctorate in 1969.
Despite his success in the medical field, it was actually in his secret life as a writer that Tsypkin’s passion lay. He began by writing poetry in the 1960s, and by the early 1970s he had switched to prose, all of which was written strictly “for the drawer” and unread by anyone but family and the most trusted friends.
After his son and daughter emigrated to the United States in 1977, Tsypkin was fired from his post and he and his wife were denied permission to emigrate themselves. Facing increasing hardship as a “refusenik” in the Brezhnev era, Tsypkin gave permission to his friend Azary Messerer and his son to seek the publication of his novel Leto v Badene (Summer in Baden-Baden) in the West. The first installment was published in the émigré journal Novaia Gazeta on March 13, 1982. Exactly one week later, on March 20, 1982 Tsypkin passed away from a heart attack, having never seen any of his fiction in print. His work would finally receive significant acclaim only in the early 2000s, thanks to the championing of it by literary critic Susan Sontag.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift and purchase from Mikhail Tsypkin; 2017. Accession MSS 2017-085.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use. Audiovisual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Russian literature -- 20th century; Authors, Russian; T︠S︡ypkin, Leonid, 1926-1982; Tsypkin, Mikhail
- Series 1. Manuscripts / Typescripts
  - Summer in Baden-Baden / Leto v Badene [typescript] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Original typescript written double-sided on thick paper for smuggling out of the USSR. Includes Tsypkin's own marks on the pages.
  - Bridge Over The Neroch / Most cherez Neroch' [typescript], 1973-08-19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Norartakir [manuscript], 1976-09-16 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Poetry [typescript], 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Short stories (Volume II) [typescript] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Contains the storeis: POPUTCHIK; POSLEDNIE KILOMETRY; SDELKA; DOZHD’; ZAPAKH ZHZHENNYKH LIST’EV; TRETII VOPROS; TARAKANY; RASSVET NAD LUAMBOI
  - Short stories and Essays (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Contains a mix of manuscripts and typescripts. Contains manuscript of short story VOSKHOZHDENIIA ANTONA PODVIGINA and typescript of AVE MARIA. Contains manuscript of the essay IA NE RUSSKII FILOSOF and a typescript of the same essay dated March 1982.
  - Poetry, 1964-1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Contains a mix of manuscripts and typescripts
  - Short stories [typescript], 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Contains the stories 1) POKHISHENIE SABINIANKI; IZ ZAPISOK PATOLOGOANATOMA; KACHELI (July 19, 1972); POPUTCHIK (1972); SDELKA (26 March 1974); AVE MARIA (23 April 1972); VASHE ZDOROV’E! (6 December 1971)’; DOZHD’; VVERKH PO REKE; PRAZDNIK, KOTORYI VSEGDA SO MNOI; ZAPAKH ZHZHENNYKH LIST’EV; TARAKANY (12 March 1978); POSLEDNIE KOLMETRY (16 December 1972); SHEKHEREZADA; PROVODY
  - Summer in Baden-Baden / Leto v Badene [typescript] (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Short stories (Volume I) [typescript] (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Contains the short stories V AVTOBUSE; SHEREZADA; VSTRECHA; PESHKOM DO METRO; IZ ZAPISOK PATLOGOANATOMA; DESIAT’ MINUT OZHIDANIIA; PROVODY; POKHISHCHENIE SABINIANKI; PRAZDNIK, KOTORYI VSEGDA SO MNOI; VASHE ZDOROV’E!; AVE MARIA; KACHELI
  - Bridge Over the Neroch / Most cherez Neroch' [typescript] (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Short stories (Volume II) [typescript] (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Contains the short stories POPUTCHIK; POSLEDNIE KILOMETRY; SDELKA; DOZHD’; ZAPAKH ZHZHENNYKH LIST’EV; TRETII VOPROS; TARAKANY; RASSVET NAD LUAMBOI
  - Bridge Over the Neroch / Most cherez Neroch' [typescript] (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Norartakir [typescript] (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Contains two copies of the novella.
    At the end of the file is also included two handwritten pages which give a key to the micrcofilms.
- Series 2. Personal and Legal Documents
  - Diplomas, 1947-1952 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Contains L.B. Tsypkin's diploma from Medical School and diploma of candidate of medical science.
  - Diplomas, 1960-1982 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Contains L.B. Tsypkin's Certificate of Senior Research Fellow; diploma of doctor of medical science; membership card for the Moscow Club of Scientists.
  - N.I. Michnikova's Diplomas, 1949-1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Contain's N.I. Michnikova's college diploma and advanced training certificate.
  - N.I. Michnikova V.M. Poliak - Government Documents (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Contains N.I. Michnikova's employment record and V.M. Poliak's old age pension ID.
  - Congratulations on receiving PhD (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Collection of congratulations recieved by L.B. Tsypkin when he completed his PhD.
  - Government Documents, 1978-11-18-1982-04-06 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Contains proof of marraige, proof of emploment, and reciept for burial of urn.
  - Resume (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Translated into English. Contains an employment history, and a translation in English of one academic article.
  - Dissertation / Izuchenie morfologii i biologicheskikh svoistv odnosloinykh kletochnykh kul’tur iz tripsinizirovannykh tkanei, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series 3. Correspondence
  - Correspondence from M.V. Iudina, 1965-11-22-1968-12-09 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Seven letters to N.I. Michnikova and L.B. Tsypkin from Maria Veniaminovna Iudina (1965 – 1968); telegram from Maria Veniaminovna Iudina to Aleksandr Isaevich Solzhenitsyn wishing him a happy birthday (9 December 1968)
  - Letters from Tsypkin and Michnikova to son, 1977-07-21-1977-12-25 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Letters from Tsypkin and Michnikova to son, 1978-01-12-1978-12-23 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Letters from Tsypkin and Michnikova to son, 1979-01-12-1979-12-21 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Letters from Tsypkin and Michnikova to son, 1980-01-15-1980-12-14 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Letters from Tsypkin and Michnikova to son, 1981-01-08-1982-07-08 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Letters from K.M. Rozental' to M.L. Tsypkin, 1977-09-04-1978-09-25 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Letters from K.M. Rozental' to M.L. Tsypkin, 1979-01-16-1979-12-09 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence surrounding the struggle to emigrate, 1978-02-24-1981-08-25 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    This file includes correspodence with (among others): Senator Edward Kennedy, Richard Pipes, Senator Daniel Moynihan, the American Jewish Committee, Senator Paul Tsongas, and Action for Soviet Jewry.
  - Correspondence surrounding the struggle to emigrate, 1981-10-26-1983-09-20 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Contains correspondence related to Tsypkin and Michnikova's struggle to emigrate with (among others): House of Representatives Speaker Thomas O'Neill, Jr, Senator Paul Tsongas, Medical Mobilization for Soviet Jewry, US Representative to the UN Committee on Human Rights Carl Gershman, State Representative Saundra Graham, Action for Soviet Jewry.
  - Condolences, 1982-03 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Also contains the eulogy given by Mikhail Tsypkin
  - N.I. Michnikova's correspondence regarding publication, 1987-05-13-1990-11-16 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M.L. Tsypkin's correspondence regarding publication, 1986-03-25-2007-09-24 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Also includes Mikhail Tsypkin's notebook which contains a list of Leonid Tsypkin's manuscripts and typescripts given to Martin Gilman and Tatyana Malkina to take out of Russia and which they lost/forgot about.
  - Correspondence between M.L. Tsypkin and L.I. Ravkina, 2001-11-11-2008-05-10 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Also contain's L.I. Ravkina's memoirs of Leonid Tsypkin
- Series 4. Publications
  - Novaia Gazeta [newspaper], 1982-03-13-1982-05-01 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Contains 8 editions of Novaia Gazeta (from March 13-19, 1982 until May 1-7, 1982) which featured the original publication of LET OV BADENE (Summer in Baden-Baden).
  - Novaia Gazeta [newspaper], 1982-05-08-1982-06-26 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Contains 8 editions of Novaia Gazeta (from May 8-14, 1982 until June 26 - July 2, 1982) which featured the original publication of LET OV BADENE (Summer in Baden-Baden). The final issue (July 6, 1982) featuring the novel is not included.
  - Viroterapiia i iskusstvennaia geterogenizatsiia opukholei, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Tezisy dokladov simpoziuma 19-20 aprelia 1977 g. (Izdatel’stvo “Zinatne”, Riga 1977)
    Publicatin of articles presented at a symposium, 19-20 April 1977. Publishing House "Zinate", Riga 1977.
  - Formations [journal], 1991 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Formations, volume 6, No. 1, Spring 1991 Contains the English translation of L.B. Tsypkin's short story THE COCKROACHES
- Series 5. Reviews and Press
  - Newspaper Reviews, 2001-11-18-2013-12-05 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Reviews of Leonid Tsypkin's fiction. This folder contains the Los Angeles Times Books Review (2001-11-18); The New York Times Book Review (2002-03-03); The New York Review of Books (2002-05-23); Kul'tura (2004-06-29); The New York Review of Books (2013-12-05).
  - Reviews from the German and Russian emigre press, 1983-1985 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Includes photocopies of reviews of L.B. Tsypkin's fiction, collected from the German and Russian emigre press between 1983 and 1985. Includes articles from Russkaia mysl'; Russland und Wir; Suddeutsche Zeitung; Der Tages Spiegel; Neue Zuercher Zeitung; Das Goldene Blatt; Judische Rundschau; Oberösterreichische Pensionisten Post; Mödlinger Stadtanzeiger; Neues Volksblatt; Oberösterreichistches Tragblatt
  - Barnes and Noble advertisement (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Advertisement for Barnes and Noble featuring Susan Sontag and her favorite books discovered in translation, which includes Leonid Tsypkin's 'Summer in Baden-Baden'
  - Reviews from the English language press, 2001-2002 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Includes photocopies of reviews from the English language, including articles by Vassily Aksyonov, The New Leader; Ignacio Schwartz, Ralph Magazine; Dan Deluca, The Philadelphia Inquirer; Dick Schneider, Winston-Salem Journal; The New York Times Book Review; Tom Gallagher, Moscow Times; Shaazka Beyerle.
  - New Directions catalogue, Fall 2001 - Winter 2002 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Catalogue of new books from New Directions Publishing feature the press release and description of Leonid Tsypkin's 'Summer in Baden-Baden'
  - Novyi Vek XX1 [journal], 2002-01 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Includes article about Leonid Tsypkin by Azarii Messerer
  - Rain Taxi Review of Books, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Iskusstvo Kino [journal], 2002 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Journal 'Iskusstvo Kino' #3, 2002. Includes an article about Tsypkin by Zara Abdullaeva ('Fantasticheskii Realizm')
  - Materials from the Dutch press, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Includes originals and photocopies of magazines and advertisements from the Dutch press, mainly connected with Saskia von Schaik's documentary film 'Tsypkin: Een Russische Vertelling'
  - Reviews from the UK press, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Photocopies of reviews from the British press, including ones by Alan Chadwick, Metro Life; Charlotte Hobson, The Telegraph; Martyn Bedford, Literary Review; John Banville, The Irish Times Book Review; Jennie Erdal, Evening Standard; Catriona Kelly, TLS; Carole Angner, The Independent
  - Reviews from the Brazilian press, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Photocopies of reviews from the Brazilian upon the publication of the Portuguese translation of 'Verão em Baden-Baden' (Leto v Badene). Compiled and bound by Companhia des Letras.
  - Materials from the Brazilian press, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Includes coverage from the Brazilian press upon publication of the Portuguese translation of Susan Sontag's book 'Diante da dor dos outros' (Regarding the Pain of Others). Compiled and bound by Companhia des Letras.
  - Reviews from the German press, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    As compiled by Berlin Verlang Publisher for Mikhail Tsypkin.
- Series 6. Library
  This series contains materials related to Leonid Tsypkin's study of Dostoevsky, including 11 hardcover books from his personal library pertaining to the subject, some of which include his own marginalia.
  - N.F. Bel’chikov – Dostoevskii v protsesse petrashevtsev [book] (Box 6, Folder 7)
    N.F. Bel’chikov – Dostoevskii v protsesse petrashevtsev (Izdatel’stvo “Nauka”: Moskva, 1971)
  - Dostoevskii v zarubezhnykh literaturakh (Redaktor: V.A. Brailovskii) [book] (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Akademiia Nauk SSSR, Institute russkoi literatury (Pushkinskii dom) – Dostoevskii v zarubezhnykh literaturakh (Leningrad “Nauka”: Leningradskoe otdelenie, 1978) (Redaktor: V.A. Brailovskii)
  - D. Bregova - Doroga iskanii: molodost' Dostoevskogo [book] (Box 7, Folder 1)
    D. Bregova - Doroga iskanii: molodost' Dostoevskogo (roman) (Sovetskii pisatel': Moskva, 1971)
  - D. Bregova - Siberskoe Likholet'e: Fedora Dostoevskogo [book] (Box 7, Folder 1)
    D. Bregova - Siberskoe Likholet'e: Fedora Dostoevskogo. Roman. (Sovetskii pisatel': Moskva, 1974)
  - Dnevnik A.G. Dostoevskoi 1867 g. [book] (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Dnevnik A.G. Dostoevskoi 1867 g. (Novaia Moskva, 1923)
    This edition has been rebound by Leonid Tsypkin and includes his own notes and marginalia.
  - A.S. Dolinin - V tvorcheskoi laboratorii Dostoevskogo (istoriia sozdaniia romana "podrostok") [book] (Box 7, Folder 3)
    A.S. Dolinin - V tvorcheskoi laboratorii Dostoevskogo (istoriia sozdaniia romana "podrostok") (Sovetskii pisatel': Leningrad, 1947)
  - Iu. Kariakin - Samoobman Raskol'nikova [book] (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Iu. Kariakin - Samoobman Raskol'nikova (Khudozhestvennaia literatura: Moskva, 1976)
  - Dostoevskii i russkie pisateli: traditsii novatorstvo masterstvo: sbornik statei (Redaktor: K.N. Polonskaia) [book] (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Dostoevskii i russkie pisateli: traditsii novatorstvo masterstvo: sbornik statei (Sovetskii pisatel': Moskva, 1971) (Redaktor: K.N. Polonskaia)
  - E. Sarukhanian - Dostoevskii v Peterburge [book] (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Evgeniia Sarukhanian - Dostoevskii v Peterburge (Lenizdat: Leningrad, 1972)
  - A.A. Staniuta - Postizhenie cheloveka: tvorchestvo Dostoevskogo 1840-1860-kh godov [book] (Box 7, Folder 5)
    A.A. Staniuta - Postizhenie cheloveka: tvorchestvo Dostoevskogo 1840-1860-kh godov (Izdatel'stvo BGU im. V.I. Lenina: Minsk, 1976)
  - Dostoevskii: Materialy i issledovaniia (3) (Redaktor: K.N. Fenomenov) [book] (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Akademiia Nauk SSSR, Institute russkoi literatury (Pushkinskii dom) – Dostoevskii: Materialy i issledovaniia (3) (Leningrad “Nauka”: Leningradskoe otdelenie, 1978) (Redaktor: K.N. Fenomenov)
  - List of books, 1979-08-31-1979-10-19 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    3 handwritten pages, compiled between 31.08.1979 and 19.10.1979 by Leonid Tsypkin and listing several book titles
  - Brochures and guidebooks from Dostoevskii Museums, 1959-1975 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    4 guidebooks and brochures from the Dostoevsky House Musuem (Muzei-kvartira F.M. Dostoevskogo) in Moscow, 1959-1976 3 brochures from the Literary Memorial Museum (Literaturno-Memorial'nyi muzei F.M. Dostoevskogo) in Leningrad, 1974-1975
  - Dostoevskii postcard collection, 1976-1982 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    One set of postcards from the Literary Memorial Museum (Literaturno-Memorial'nyi muzei F.M. Dostoevskogo), 1976 One set of postcards from the State Literary Museum (Gosudarstvennyi Literaturnyi Muzei), 1982
  - I.N. Viazinin - Staraia Russa [guidebook] (Box 7, Folder 6)
    I.N. Viazinin - Staraia Russa (Lenizdat, 1980).
    Includes several of Leonid Tsypkin's page-markings.
  - I.M. Reinus - Dostoevskii v Staroi Russe [guidebook] (Box 7, Folder 6)
    I.M. Reinus - Dostoevskii v Staroi Russe (Lenizdat, 1971).
    Includes Leonid Tsypkin's own page-marking and notes.
- Series 7. Photographs
  - Dostoevsky in Petersburg [photos and text] (Box 8, Folder 1)
    From Leonid Tsypkin's presentation on Dostoevsky at the Dostoevsky Museum in Leningrad; each page contains a photograph and a textual description of the photo. Photos taken in 1975; presentation given in November 1979.
  - Dostoevsky in Petersburg [text] (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Contains 2 copies (1 bound in blue notebook) of the printed text of the descriptions to each of the photos included in the 'Dostoevsky in Petersburg' file.
  - Po mestam Dostoevskogo i ego geroev v Peterburge [text] (Box 8, Folder 2)
    This is the text of the speech given by Leonid Tsypkin as he showed his photos 'Dostoevsky in Petersburg' at the Dostoevsky Museum in Leningrad, November 1979.
  - Dostoevsky in Petersburg [photos] (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Two copies of the photographs; found with the text to the Leonid Tsypkin's presentation 'Po mestam Dostoevskogo v Peterburge,' all have Leonid Tsypkin's handwritten notes on the back.
  - Pamiatnye mesta Dostoevskogo v Leningrade [photos] (Box 8, Folder 3)
    A series of photographs similar to the other files of marked 'Dostoevsky in Petersburg.' This includes photos at the beginning of the descrpition of each photo to come next.
  - Dostoevsky in Petersburg [slides] (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Contains slides 5-30 of the same images as seen elsewhere labelled 'Dostoevsky in Petersburg.'
  - Dostoevsky in Moscow [photos] (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Contains 2 sets of an ordered collection photographs, all with Leonid Tsypkin's hand written descriptions on the back.
  - Pamiatnye mesta Dostoevskogo v Moskve [photos] (Box 8, Folder 4)
    A collectionf of photographs similar to those found in the file labelled 'Dostoevsky in Moscow'. This includes photographs at the beginning which are merely photos of the descriptions of those that follow.
  - Plenka N.1 / Film roll N.1 [photos and text] (Box 8, Folder 4)
    A collection of photos mostly from around Moscow. The photos themselves are in order, and preceded by a one page list of their descriptions.
  - Dostoevsky in Staraia Russa [photos and text] (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
    Contains the notebook and photographs from Leonid Tsypkin's trip to Staraia Russa in the fall of 1981. The notebook from the trip includes lists of photos and notes, but provides no definitive key to the one included here. The photographs have been sorted by Natalia Michnikova. Her notes are provided preceding the photograph they apply to, when applicable.
  - Assorted numbered photographs [photos] (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    This is the largest collection of photos in the series, but they are undated and no description is given other than the number on the back which keeps them in order (of which are great many are missing). A few, particularly the portraits, include notes on the back, though this is the exception, not the rule.
  - Photocopies of assorted numbered photographs [photocopies] (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Photocopies of the file 'Assorted numbered photos' in black and white ink, with some notes added by Mikhail Tsypkin.
  - Other photographs [photos] (Box 9, Folder 4)